Hello everyone, and welcome. I’m Dr. Michael
Greger, coming to you live from my treadmill — the
last time you will see me in Seattle. I am
moving to rural Virginia next month, and so
you’ll be able to check out my new pad, an actual
little house — no more rentals — if you manage to
catch my next webinar, which will be on May
13th on hair loss. Mark your calendar: May 13th.
But hey, long time no see. It’s been so long
since my last webinar that I shaved off my beard
and it grew all back. Hashtag pandemic life.
Normally you’d see me — I do interviews all
the time and monthly Q&As — but I’ve been AWOL
finishing up what is shaping up to be the most
comprehensive book I have ever written, which is
saying something: How Not to Age. Unfortunately,
I’m over the deadline, scrambling to write the
last few chapters. Still hoping to have it out by
the end of the year, but no promises. I’ve got
to get back to writing, so let’s get started.
First, some quick housekeeping logistics. If at
any time you run into technical difficulties,
there are live chat Zoom staff standing by.
Let me paste the link into the chat box for
you. All right — if they’re not able to help. We
also have NutritionFacts staff standing by too,
though presumably if Zoom can’t help, I don’t
know what they can do — but they can give you
some emotional support. Here is that info
again, pasting it into the chat as well.
All right, please reserve the Q&A button you
see in the Zoom window there to ask content
questions. Today’s webinar is only an hour, but
I am reserving some time for Q&A at the end,
so feel free to add your questions in the
Q&A throughout the webinar — you don’t have
to wait until the end. The NutritionFacts team
will compile them to be answered at the end.
You don’t have to worry about taking notes
or anything. After the webinar is over,
we’re not only going to send you a full
recording of it, but also a free link to
download all the videos in high-def, so you can
see the videos in all their full-resolution glory.
All right, let me start with a video
entitled "Fewer Than One in 5,000
Meet Sodium and Potassium Recommended
Intakes". Play video one. Let’s do it.
Worldwide, physical inactivity accounted
for more than 10 million years
of healthy life lost, but what we eat
accounts for nearly 20 times that.
Unhealthy diets shave hundreds of
millions of disability-free years off
of people's lives every year.
What are the worst aspects of our diets?
Four out of the five of the deadliest
dietary traps involve not eating
enough of certain foods.
Not eating enough whole grains,
not eating enough fruits,
not eating enough nuts and seeds,
and not eating enough vegetables.
But our most fatal flaw
is too much salt.
That's on the order of 15 times
deadlier than diets too high in soda,
for example, just to keep
things in perspective.
There remains no single more
effective public health action
related to nutrition than the
reduction of sodium in the diet.
This is why national and international
health organizations have called
for warning labels on salt
packets and salt shakers,
with messages like "Too much sodium
in the diet causes high blood pressure
and increases risk of stomach
cancer, stroke, heart disease,
and kidney disease.
Limit your use."
Salt also increases inflammation.
For example, sodium intake
is associated with increased disease
activity in multiple sclerosis,
an inflammatory autoimmune
nerve condition,
about three to four times
the exacerbation rate in those
with medium or high sodium intakes
compared to those getting less than
a teaspoon of salt total in a day.
Just as you can see higher sodium
levels in the tissues of those
who suffer from lupus, another serious
inflammatory autoimmune disease,
you can correlate high sodium levels
in the spinal cord of MS patients
with the disease and decreased
structural integrity.
Where's sodium found though?
Really crappy foods.
So it's hard to know
if increased salt intake
is just a marker for
a bad diet overall.
But what we do know is that
salt and high blood pressure
are cause-and-effect.
How?
Because we have more than a
hundred randomized controlled trials
demonstrating that if you cut down on
added salt, your blood pressures fall,
and the more you cut down, the better.
Part of the mechanism may actually be
the damage salt may do to your
microbiome, the friendly flora
in your gut.
And no wonder.
Our bodies evolved only to
handle about 750 mg a day.
The American Heart Association
says we should stay under
at least twice that about,
but we're eating more than
four times what's natural.
And it's only getting worse,
increasing over the last decade.
Anyone care to guess what
percentage of Americans exceed
the 1,500 mg upper
limit recommendation?
98.8%. And that was
more than a decade ago.
The vast majority of U.S. adults
consume too much sodium, and
at the same time, too little potassium,
a mineral that lowers blood pressure.
Less than 2% of U.S. adults
consumed the recommended
daily minimum intake of potassium.
So more than 98% of Americans
eat potassium deficient diets.
This deficiency is even more striking
when comparing our current intake
with that of our ancestors, who consumed
large amounts of dietary potassium.
We evolved getting probably
more than 10,000 mg a day.
The recommendation is to get
around at least around half that,
yet most of us don't even
come anywhere close.
Put the two guidelines together,
and sodium and potassium goals
are currently met by less than
0.015% of the U.S. population.
So we're talking close
to 99.99% noncompliance,
as in only 1 in 6,000 Americans even
hits the recommended guidelines.
What about using potassium-based
salt substitutes?
Instead of using
sodium chloride—salt—
why not shake on
some potassium chloride?
Seems a little too good to be true.
I mean, same salty taste, but you're
reducing sodium while at the same time
increasing your potassium intake?
Is there a catch?
Are potassium-based salt
substitutes safe? Effective?
We'll find out next.
(Dr. Greger introduces next video)
Of all the terrible things about
our diets, high dietary sodium intake,
high salt intake, is the leading risk,
estimated to be causing millions
of deaths every year, killing millions
mainly through adverse effects on
blood pressure and increased
risk of stroke, heart attack, and
kidney damage. Hypertension—
high blood pressure—
is still called the
"silent and invisible killer"
because it rarely causes symptoms,
but is one of the most powerful
independent predictors of some
of our leading causes of death.
We evolved consuming a diet very
rich in potassium and low in sodium,
but today this pattern has
been completely reversed.
This flip reflects a shift from
traditional plant-based diets
high in potassium
and low in sodium,
a shift from fruits, greens,
roots, and tubers
to salty processed foods stripped
of potassium, which is considered
a nutrient of public health concern
because 98% of the U.S. population
doesn't even reach the recommended
minimum daily intake of potassium,
as I mentioned in the last video.
And low potassium intake itself is
implicated in high blood pressure
and cardiovascular disease, yet
few physicians actually think about
proposing their patients eat more
foods that are potassium rich,
like fruits and vegetables, to
better control blood pressure,
even though several meta-analyses
have now confirmed
that high potassium intake appears
to reduce the risk of stroke.
There's even a reduction in stroke risk
independent of blood pressure effects,
consistent with other protective
effects of potassium,
such as reducing clot formation,
reducing hardening of the arteries,
reducing the generation
of free radicals.
Higher sodium intake is associated
with a 20% increased risk
of dying prematurely,
where higher potassium intake
was associated with a 20%
reduced risk of dying prematurely.
Yeah, but sodium is found
in crappy processed foods,
while potassium is concentrated in
healthy foods like beans and greens.
So having low sodium intake and high
potassium intake may just be a marker
for a healthful diet: more
plant foods and less crap.
How do we know sodium
is cause-and-effect bad?
Because randomized controlled trials
show sodium reduction leads
to blood pressure reduction,
just like there are randomized
controlled trials showing that if
you give people extra potassium,
you can bring down their
blood pressures as well.
So what about using potassium
chloride to salt your food,
rather than sodium chloride?
That's what's found in these
zero sodium salt substitutes.
Potassium chloride is a
naturally occurring mineral salt,
which is obtained the same way
we get regular sodium salt.
Since we get too much sodium
and not enough potassium,
this would seem to make potassium
chloride a win-win solution.
Now, whole healthy plant foods
would be the best way
to increase potassium intake.
Fruits and vegetables have all sorts
of other good things in them besides
potassium, but we have 10 studies
now, randomized controlled trials,
showing that just swapping in some
potassium chloride for regular salt
can lead to significant reductions
in blood pressure in people
with hypertension, suggesting
that salt substitutes may even help
prevent hypertension as well.
We know salt substitutes
can lower blood pressure,
but does it actually decrease
the incidence of hypertension,
and more importantly, disease
endpoints like stroke and mortality?
You don't know until
you put it to the test.
In a randomized controlled trial,
households had their salt replaced
with just a quarter potassium chloride.
At that level, most people either
can't tell the difference or even prefer
the salt with the potassium mixed in.
Okay, but did it actually do any good?
The use of even the quarter
salt substitute was associated
with cutting the risk of
developing hypertension in half.
Okay, but what about actually following
people out to see if there's any change
in the risk of dying from
cardiovascular disease?
Five kitchens in a veterans' retirement
home were randomized into two groups
for about two and a half years,
salting meals with regular salt
or, unbeknownst to the
cooks and the diners,
a 50/50 blend of potassium chloride.
Those in the half potassium group cut
their risk of dying from cardiovascular
disease by about 40% and lived
up to nearly a year longer.
The life expectancy difference
at age 70 was equivalent to that
which would have naturally
occurred in 14 years,
meaning that just switching
to half potassium salt appeared
to effectively make people more
than a decade younger
when it came to risk of death.
As we speak, there's a massive
randomized controlled trial wrapping up
in China involving 600 villages and
more than 20,000 people that will
give us an idea of just how low we
can drop stroke risk with this strategy.
China is perfect because up to 75%
of their sodium intake comes from
salt they add in the home
kitchen or dining room,
whereas most sodium in the
American diet comes
prepackaged in the meat
and processed foods we buy,
though certainly the food companies
could switch over themselves.
Why haven't they? And why
haven't more people embraced
these salt substitutes if they work
well and can taste just as good?
We could be "Achieving the Benefits
of a High-Potassium Paleolithic
Diet, Without the Toxicity."
So "Is salt substitution ready
for prime time" or what?
What about safety?
Yes, there are convincing
arguments about the benefits,
but what about the
risks, like, you know,
the "inclusion of potentially fatal
salt substitutes in the food supply."
Wait, what?
We'll talk about the
potential downsides next.
(Dr. Greger recaps and introduces next video)
Based on how we evolved, the
Optimum Dietary Potassium Intake
likely greatly exceeds current
and even recommended intakes.
The problem is we replaced many
of the potassium-rich plant foods
we used to stuff our faces with,
like fruits, leafy greens,
and other vegetables,
including roots and tubers,
with calorie-dense junk---
stripped not only of fiber
but also potassium---such
as added fats and sugars.
So in a traditional,
largely plant-based diet,
potassium content is high
and sodium content is low.
But now, high blood pressure's
the second leading cause of death
in the world, killing more than
10 million people a year,
second only to unhealthy diets,
the #1 killer of humanity.
We can improve both by eating more
whole healthy plant foods like beans
and greens, which are packed with
potassium, which lowers blood pressure.
But since most of us are getting
too much sodium along with
too little potassium, what about
using salt substitutes?
After all, the most commonly used
salt substitute is potassium chloride,
so you'd be swapping out
sodium for potassium.
And it works.
Based on a meta-analysis of
more than a dozen randomized
controlled trials, replacing sodium
chloride with potassium chloride
lowers blood pressure.
And most of the trials involved
just swapping out regular salt
for less than 30% potassium
chloride, and they still got results.
And at less than 30%, most people
can't even tell the difference
between regular salt
and the potassium salt.
So it can taste exactly the same
and drop your blood pressures?
What's the catch?
Potassium chloride is generally
considered as safe by the FDA,
with the only major concern for
healthy people being that if you
go completely 100% sodium free
and use straight potassium chloride,
like all these, it can
taste kind of funny,
adding a bitter or metallic taste.
I've found that it depends on
what I'm seasoning with it.
It works perfectly well on some
things, but makes other things
completely inedible.
When I learned about the sodium
science and threw out my salt shaker
for good, within a few weeks
my palate totally changed,
and everything tasted fine
without salt—except pesto.
For some reason, pesto without salt
just never tasted like it used to, to me.
So I tried the potassium chloride salt
substitute, and it worked perfectly;
I couldn't tell the difference at all,
so I had the best of both worlds.
Then I remembered how as a kid
I used to put a tiny sprinkle of salt
on watermelon like they do in
the South to make it even sweeter.
So I tried it with the potassium
salt and almost gagged.
So it's definitely not for everything.
The reason healthy people
don't have to worry about
getting too much potassium
is that our kidneys just
pee out the excess.
Okay, but that's with potassium
in food. What about supplements?
No adverse effects have been
shown for long-term intakes
of potassium supplements
as high as 3,000 mg a day.
And in fact, blood levels of potassium
are maintained in the normal range
by healthy kidneys even when
potassium intake is increased
to approximately 15,000 mg a day,
which is no surprise since we evolved
eating so many healthy plant foods,
so many fruits and vegetables
that the normal, natural potassium
intake for the human species
may be on the order
of 15,000 mg a day.
Basically, the normal range
for potassium levels in the blood
is between 3.5 and 5.0,
and you start to worry when
it starts creeping up towards 6.
But give people potassium
supplements, like all the salt
substitution trials that have been
giving study subjects an average
of about 2,000 mg
of potassium a day,
and blood levels only go up 0.14.
So they might go up from 4 to 4.14,
not something that would
push you into trouble.
Now there's a limit.
If you have a "massive banana eating
habit", you could bump your potassium
from normal to above 6, but that was
evidently from years of not eating
much of anything except
up to 20 bananas a day.
Eating ten pounds of carrots every
day is also probably not a good idea.
That's like 75 carrots in one day,
which you could only do with a juicer,
which is what this person attempted
to do as part of a quack cancer cure.
What about overdoing salt substitutes?
This report from the 1940's
was on lithium poisoning
from the use of salt substitutes.
Why? Because lithium chloride was
used as a salt substitute — Jesus!
But what about potassium chloride,
which is what's used today?
There is one fatal case of someone
who committed suicide by downing
a little more than a tablespoon of a
potassium chloride salt substitute.
That doesn't seem like a lot,
just a tablespoon?
I mean, how can we keep
that on the shelves
if only a tablespoon will kill you?
Well, even less than that of regular
salt taken at once can kill you, too.
In fact, salt water ingestion was
evidently a traditional method
of suicide in ancient China,
though these days
one may be more likely
to die that way
from abusive religious practices.
Having said all that, there are
a small number of the population
who may run into problems,
primarily those with severely
impaired kidney function.
That's why there's been such
a reluctance to push
potassium-based salt substitutes
on a population level.
If your kidneys can't regulate
your potassium,
then you can definitely run
into a serious issue.
We're talking about folks with
known kidney disease, diabetes---
since diabetes can lead to kidney
damage---severe heart failure,
those on medications that impair
potassium excretion, older adults,
and individuals with
adrenal insufficiency.
If you aren't sure if you're at risk,
ask your doctor about getting
your kidney function tested.
Ironically, potassium is so
good at reducing deaths
from high blood pressure, even
among those with kidney disease,
using potassium chloride salt
substitutes would probably
still save more lives despite the risk.
Traditional dietary recommendations
to kidney patients limited the intake
of fruits and vegetables because
of their high potassium content.
However, this paradigm is
rapidly changing due to
the multiple benefits derived from
a fundamentally plant-based diet.
A whole food plant-based diet may even
ameliorate chronic kidney disease.
There's increasing evidence
that a whole food plant-based diet
may offer benefits like slowing the
progression of chronic kidney disease
and delaying kidney failure.
So the practice of restricting dietary
potassium in kidney patients
should really be reserved for patients
with documented hyperkalemia,
a potassium level of 6 or higher,
because the key to halting
progression of chronic kidney disease
may in fact lie in the produce aisle.
(Dr. Greger recaps and takes a break for Q&A session)
(Q&A session not transcribed)